Despite the Municipal Corporation of Gurugram having tried different models and agencies over the years, the mountain of untreated garbage at the Bandhwari site continues to build up, posing a serious threat to the environment and the health of residents.

No tangible solution in sight to manage municipal waste generated in the Millennium City six years after a fire closed down the treatment plant
More than six years after a fire at the Bandhwari landfill site off the Gurugram-Faridabad road led to the shutting down of the treatment plant here, the Municipal Corporation of Gurugram has failed to find a tangible solution to solid municipal waste management in the Millennium City.

Despite the civic body having tried different models and agencies over the years, the mountain of untreated garbage continues to build up, posing a serious threat to the environment and the health of the residents.

Untreated waste
Every day around 2,000 tonnes of solid municipal waste — 1,200 tonnes from Gurugram and 800 tonnes from Faridabad — is being added to the Bandhwari landfill site, which already has around 35 lakh tonnes of untreated waste. Ecogreen Energy Private Limited, the agency hired for waste treatment in the city, manages to handle just 500 tonnes per day.

Hired in August 2017, Ecogreen Energy is bound by an agreement with the MCG to set up a Waste-to-Energy (WTE) plant at the landfill site within two years, generating power from the solid municipal waste. The project, however, is yet to take off because of the failure of the civic body to procure the mandatory environmental clearance certificate.

Environmental clearance
Stressing that the delay in getting the environmental clearance was the root cause of the ever burgeoning mountain of garbage, Chief Operational Officer, Ecogreen Energy, Gaurav Joshi said since the site for the WTE plant fell within 10 km radius of Asola wildlife sanctuary in Delhi, the clearance certificate from the National Board of Wildlife was mandatory before they could start the work on it.

“It will take at least 18 months after the certificate to construct and make the WTE plant functional. Till the time the plant becomes operational, there is little that can be done to deal with the waste adding to this heap every day,” said Mr. Joshi.

When contacted, MCG Commissioner Yashpal Yadav maintained that the clearance was to be given by the Ministry of Environment and Forests and it had supported the plan actively. He added that the clearance was expected before June.

Besides the blame game over the environmental clearance, the two agencies also traded charges over delay in payments, segregation of waste at source and lack of cooperation from the residents.

Mr. Joshi claimed that more than ₹19 crore was pending as tipping fee arrears towards the MCG, making it difficult to run daily operations, and the recovery of user charges from the residents too was just around 10%, indicating a lack of coordination between the two agencies.

“The MCG pays us just ₹670 for every ₹1,000 bill raised,” said Mr. Joshi.

He also accused the MCG of failing to ensure segregation of waste at source, as per the Solid Waste Management Rules (SWM), 2016 regulations, and pointed out lack of space at the landfill site as another challenge for the agency to efficiently run its operations.

Vehemently denying all charges, Mr. Yadav said that the MCG made the payments on time and “not a single penny” was pending. He said the MCG had supported Ecogreen Energy over non-payment by the residents, but people were paying the charges where they were satisfied with the services. Mr. Yadav blamed Ecogreen Energy over non-segregation of waste at source saying the agency did not have separate compartments for it in all its vehicles yet.

Groundwater pollution
Amid all this, the contamination of groundwater in the area around the landfill site due to leachate from the garbage has emerged as a serious threat to the residents and the environment. Taking a serious view of the matter, the NGT, in its order in April, directed the MCG and Ecogreen Energy to take immediate measures to tackle the problem. Digging of leachate collection ponds, leachate spraying and reshaping of the garbage hill are among some of the measures at different stages to deal with the menace.

Running the ‘Why Waste Your Waste’ campaign for past several years, Ruchika Sethi, a citizen volunteer, said that waste generator was pivotal to any solution to manage waste and stressed the need for a legal framework to effectively address the issue.

“Scientific waste management begins with well-established responsibility of each and every waste generator. The bulk of Gurugram residents do not know the SWM policy when the global crisis of climate change is begging a paradigm shift from waste management to resource management,” said Ms. Sethi, adding: “To enable this, waste must be segregated at home. It starts from our homes, the way we dispose our waste. Also, there is a lack of legislative support and political will to effectively implement and enforce the 'SWM Rules of 2016'. The MCG has till date not formulated the by-laws with respect to the government of India’s Rules of 2016 on SWM, plastic, construction and demolition waste and e-waste.”

Party insiders distance themselves from his tweet, attribute it to his ‘inexperience’
Newly elected BJP MP from East Delhi, Gautam Gambhir, on Monday sought “exemplary action” against those behind the alleged assault of a Gurugram resident returning from a mosque after offering prayers on Saturday.

His request, however, did not go down well with his own party. The party was seemingly split down the middle on whether the former Indian cricketer had acted out of naivete or toed the party line in sync with Prime Minister Narendra Modi’s attempt at distancing himself from the comments of “some hard liners such as Pragya Thakur”.

A cross-section of party insiders, including Mr. Gambhir’s colleagues in the Parliament, either sought to distance themselves from his tweet or to attribute it to his “inexperience”. There was, however, a small section of party insiders who argued that “he had done nothing wrong” because the BJP was “not a divisive force” as some “individuals with vested interests” were “trying to prove”.

“In Gurugram Muslim man told to remove skullcap,chant Jai Shri Ram. It is deplorable. Exemplary action needed by Gurugram authorities,” Mr. Gambhir tweeted. “We are a secular nation where @Javedakhtarjadu writes ‘ओ पालन हारे, निर्गुण और न्यारे’ & @RakeyshOmMehra gave us d song ‘अर्ज़ियाँ’ in Delhi 6,” Mr. Gambhir added.

Mohammad Barkat (25) was allegedly accosted by a group of men while returning from the Jama Masjid in Gurugram on Saturday evening. He was allegedly referred to with a derogatory term, asked to remove his skull cap and chant “Jai Shri Ram” before being assaulted. The incident allegedly occurred in the Jacubpura area around 10 p.m. and the accused are still at large.

The police have registered a case under relevant IPC sections, including charges of promoting religious hatred, causing hurt, criminal intimidation, among others, at a local police station in Gurugram.

In a subsequent tweet, Mr. Gambhir wrote, “My thoughts on secularism emanate from honourable PM Mr Modi’s mantra ‘सबका साथ, सबका विकास, सब का विश्वास’. I am not limiting myself to Gurugram incident alone, any oppression based on caste/religion is deplorable. Tolerance & inclusive growth is what idea of India is based on.”

Delhi BJP chief and North East Delhi MP Manoj Tiwari issued a statement arguing that “some people” may be trying to paint the incident in a communal light. “Mr. Gambhir has reacted with his innocence on this matter. The Delhi BJP condemns such incidents in the society,” he said.

A senior party hand said, “Mr. Gambhir should take some time to observe the functioning of the party. After all, he is an MP now.”

While some of his colleagues said they were not aware of Mr. Gambhir’s tweet, others argued that he could not have “said what he said independently”. “We are all representatives of the party and it is highly unlikely that Mr. Gambhir tweeted without seeking a go-ahead from the high command,” he said.

A senior party leader advised Mr. Gambhir to “wait” for the conclusion of police probe into the case.. “It is not only wrong to judge such incidents based on whether they are motivated by hate and communal considerations or by circumstances. There seems to be an attempt to colour many local incidents communal since the BJP received the massive people’s mandate,” he said.

Another leader, however, said Mr. Gambhir has merely “stated the party’s line” in the matter. “The BJP is not a divisive, communal force as some people want to make it seem to be. What wrong has he done by tweeting what he did? Even the Prime Minister has, recently, expressed his regret at pro-[Nathuram] Godse comments made by some hard line leaders. There is nothing wrong in what Mr. Gambhir said,” the leader argued.

Eminent gynaecologist and noted author Dr. Arun Gadre was reportedly surrounded by a gang of youths in New Delhi’s Connaught Place area and asked his religion while being forced to chant ‘Jai Shri Ram’.

While the Pune-based Dr. Gadre did not file a police complaint regarding the incident which occurred on the morning of May 26, he confided to a close friend of his.

“He [Dr. Gadre] was staying at the YMCA near Jantar Mantar as he was due to deliver a lecture organized by Indian Medical Association at Bijnor the next day. When he left for his morning stroll, he was accosted by a gang of five-six youth near the Hanuman Temple in Connaught Place. They surrounded him, asked him what religion he was and finally demanded that he chant ‘Jai Shri Ram,” said senior journalist, Anant Bagaitkar, to whom Dr. Gadre later narrated the incident.

Mr. Bagaitkar further said that Dr. Gadre, who had a bypass surgery recently, was “shocked and scared”. Issuing a late evening response on reaching Pune on Monday, Dr. Gadre downplayed the incident as “trivial”.

“On 26 May, I was taking a morning walk in Delhi at around 6 a.m. near the YMCA. Suddenly, few youths [confronted me] and asked me to say ‘Jai Shri Ram’. I was a little taken aback and said it. They insisted I say it loudly. I just walked away and they let me. I was not physically manhandled…I did not want to make it public nor report it to the police because I thought it to be trivial…I request everyone to treat it as trivial and not draw any conclusion,” read Dr. Gadre’s response when asked about the incident.

Dr. Gadre, who has worked with the renowned Dr. Prakash Amte, has worked for the promotion of the patient’s rights, universal healthcare and the social regulation of the private medical sector.

Known for his concern about the decline of medical ethics, he is the co-author (along with Dr. Abhay Shukla) of the expose on the rot within the medical profession titled Dissenting Diagnosis.

Dr. Gadre, along with his wife Dr. Jyotsna Gadre, has practiced in drought-prone areas in Maharashtra’s rural hinterland for several years.

Amends ‘Unified Building Bye-Laws for Delhi 2016’; notifies new fire safety rules
Banning of kitchens and cooking in rooftops and basements of commercial buildings are among some of the measures taken by the Delhi government on Monday, in wake of the Surat fire tragedy that killed 22 students.

The Delhi government on Monday amended the “Unified Building Bye-Laws (UBBL) for Delhi 2016” for commercial buildings to include the changes.

“No kitchen will be allowed on rooftops or basements. No cooking activity of any kind will be permitted on rooftop or basement,” the amendment read. Storage of inflammable materials will not be allowed on rooftops.


Inflammable materials
“No temporary roofing over the roof or terrace using fibre reinforced plastic (FRP) or any inflammable material will be allowed,” read another point in the amendment. The amendment also banned use of inflammable materials such as wooden panels, foam panels and carpets in passages, corridors or staircases.

“In Arpit Hotel fire tragedy [February 2019 that killed 17 people], the staircase was carpeted that led to generating more smoke. As a result, one could not even use the exit routes,” said Urban Development Minister Satyendar Jain.

Also, fire NOC for guest houses will not be issued to buildings, which have more than four floors (excluding basement and stilt floor), as per the amendment.

“In many places in Delhi, after giving money to municipal corporation, people have built six floors. But according to the rules, more than four floors are not allowed,” the Minister said.

The amendment also made it mandatory to have carbon monoxide detectors in all rooms and also natural or mechanical arrangements for smoke ventilation in all corridors and passages at each level and staircases.

The Minister said that when a building catches fire, most of the people die due to carbon monoxide suffocation than burns.

Also, there should be doors with fire-resistance rating of at least one hour at the entrance of staircases of each floor if there are more than 10 people living on the floor, according to the amendment.

2 Faridabad head constables suspended, 3 SPOs dismissed
Two head constables were suspended and three Special Police Officers (SPOs) dismissed from service after a video featuring them beating up a woman in custody went viral on Monday.

A case was also registered against the accused policemen on charges of wrongful confinement, causing hurt and insult the modesty of a woman. Two of the policemen — SPOs Harpal and Dinesh — were arrested. Head constables Baldev, Rohit and SPO Krishan are on the run.

Hitting with belt
The over four-minute-long video features a woman being interrogated by three policemen, two of them in plain clothes, with one of them hitting her with a belt for not sharing information. In the video, the woman is heard sharing a contact number with the police and pleading that she does not have any other information on the subject.

But the policemen refuse to believe her and hit her.

One of the policemen, whose face is not visible, can be heard saying that the woman was “acting too smart” and not sharing the information intentionally.

The video dates back to October last year when the police team at Adarsh Nagar police station had received a tip-off about a couple indulging in an illegal act in a park.

A raid was conducted and the woman was detained, but the man managed to escape. No complaint has been received by the police in this connection.

‘Acted against the law’
Taking cognisance of the video, Faridabad Police Commissioner Sanjay Kumar said the cops in the video have acted against the law of interrogation. Beating up the woman had brought bad name to the entire police fraternity. He said the interrogation must have been carried out in the presence of a woman police officer.

Efforts are being made to contact the woman featuring in the video to seek more details about the matter, said Faridabad police spokesperson Sube Singh.

Officials deployed on PCR duty killed one of them; 2 others managed to escape
Two wanted criminals were shot dead after a fierce gun battle on a busy road beneath Dwarka Mor metro station on Sunday evening.

The police said that a wanted criminal identified as Parveen Gehlot, a resident of Nawada, was in his car when three criminals in another car intercepted him at a traffic signal beneath Dwarka Mor metro station and opened fire at him.

Police fire 3 rounds
Police officials in a PCR van near the metro station also fired three rounds at the criminals and shot one of them dead. The shooter has been identified as Vikas Dalal, a wanted criminal.

“The incident took place at 4 p.m. when the occupants of a black car opened fire at a white car from inside the vehicle. Later, one of the occupants with a pistol in his hand came out and shot the car driver from a close range. Total 15 rounds were fired at the man who was seated in the white car,” said a police officer.

Gunshot sounds on the busy street created chaos as passers-by and motorists ran for their lives. Constable Naresh who was deployed on PCR duty at Dwarka Mor metro station challenged the criminals from the other side of the road. “One of the shooter opened fire at Naresh and in retaliation he opened fire. While one of them died on the spot, the other two managed to flee in their car,” said a police officer.

Joint CP (Western Range) Madhup Tiwari said both the deceased are criminals and have several cases of murders, extortion and robberies registered against them at various police stations in Delhi and Haryana.

He added that Vikas Dalal was the most wanted criminal and has been on the run since he escaped from the custody of Haryana Police from a court in Faridabad in 2018.

Cop to be rewarded
“The policeman who shot dead the criminal at the spot will be awarded and his name will be recommended for the out-of-turn promotion,” said Mr. Tiwari.

DCP (Dwarka) Anto Alphonse, said that a case under IPC section 302 (murder) has been registered at Bindapur police station against two persons who accompanied the shooter, who was shot dead by policeman.

“We have identified the other two shooters. The murder was a fallout of a property dispute between the two gangs for the last several months,” said the DCP.

